<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-fixed-ippm-ioam-fixed-option-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Fixed IOAM Option">In Situ Operations, Administration, and Maintenance (IOAM) Fixed-Length Option</title>

    <author fullname="Author Author" initials="A."
            surname="Author">
      <organization abbrev="">Affiliation</organization>

      <address>
        <email>email@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2025"/>

    <area>OPS</area>

    <workgroup>IPPM</workgroup>

    <keyword>IOAM</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>In situ measurement is performed by incorporating performance related 
	  information into in-flight data packets. This document specifies a 
	  new IOAM Option-Type that has a fixed length and can be updated by
	  transit nodes along the path. It enables lightweight monitoring using constant-length 
	  data that does not depend on the number of hops in the network.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
	  <t>In Situ Operations, Administration, and Maintenance (IOAM) 
	  <xref target="RFC9197"/> is used for measuring and monitoring a network
	  by incorporating measurement and operational data into some or all of
	  the data packets. <xref target="RFC9197"/> has defined several
	  Option-Types, intended for different purposes.</t>

	  <t>This document introduces a new IOAM Option-Type that can be 
	  incorporated into data packets and updated by transit
	  nodes along the path. Compared to existing IOAM Trace Option-Types, the 
	  new Option-Type provides coarse-grained performance information using 
	  data fields that have a constant length.</t>
	  
	  <t>There are several in-progress proposals that use a fixed-size
	  telemetry header, including <xref target="I-D.cxx-ippm-ioamaggr"/>, 
	  <xref target="I-D.mzbc-ippm-transit-measurement-option"/>,
	  <xref target="I-D.xiao-ippm-ioam-trace-extensions"/>,
	  <xref target="I-D.filsfils-ippm-path-tracing"/>
	  and <xref target="I-D.ravi-ippm-csig"/>.
	  These proposals can potentially benefit from a generic 
	  IOAM Fixed-Length Option-Type.</t>
	  

    </section>

    <section anchor="Conventions" title="Conventions">
      <section title="Requirement Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
        14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
        when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Terminology">
	  
        <t>Abbreviations used in this document:</t>

        <t><list hangIndent="11" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="IOAM:">In-situ Operations, Administration, and
            Maintenance</t>

            <t hangText="OAM:">Operations, Administration, and Maintenance</t>

          </list></t>

	    <t>The terms Option-Type, encapsulating 
		node, decapsulating node, and transit node are defined in 
		<xref target="RFC9197"/>.</t>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="option" title="In situ Fixed-Length Option-Type">
      <t>This document defines a new IOAM Option-Type, the
	  Fixed-Length Option-Type. The length of the Fixed-Length 
	  Option-Type MUST NOT be modified by IOAN transit nodes.
	  However, IOAM transit nodes MAY modify the option data
	  in the Fixed-Length Option-Type.
	  <xref target="FixedFormat"/> presents the
	  format of this Option-Type.</t>

          <figure align="center" anchor="FixedFormat"
                  title="Fixed-Length Option-Type">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
         
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |        Namespace-ID           |    IOAM Fixed-Length-Type     |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                                                               |
   |    Option data depending on the Fixed-Length-Type value       |
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   
           ]]></artwork>
          </figure>

      <t>
	     An IOAM node that complies to this draft MUST support the following
		 fields, as depicted in <xref target="FixedFormat"/>:
		 
		 <list style="hanging">
		   <t hangText="Namespace-ID:">A 16-bit namespace identifier, as 
		   defined in <xref target="RFC9197"/>.</t>


         <t hangText="IOAM Fixed-Length-Type">16-bit identifier that specifies 
		 which data types are used in the Fixed-Length Option-Type. A new 
		 registry is defined for this field, as specified in 
		 <xref target="IANA"/>.</t>
                </list></t>

	  <t>The option data that follows the Fixed-Length-Type has a constant
      length that is not modified by transit nodes. The semantics and length
      of the option data are determined by the specific Fixed-Length-Type value.
      The option data might consist of more than one sub-field. The specification
      of the Fixed-Length-Type values and the corresponding option data formats
      is outside the scope of this document.</t>
	    
	  <t>As in <xref target="RFC9197"/>, the Fixed-Length Option-Type can
      be incorporated into all or a subset of the traffic that is forwarded
      by the encapsulating node. Notably, this option adds a fixed and 
	  low overhead to data packets, which remains constant along the path.</t>
	  
	  
	  
		  
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
        <t>To be added to a future version of this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations of IOAM in general are discussed in 
	  <xref target="RFC9197"/>. The Fixed-Length Option-Type may be used for reconnaissance, which
	  in turn can facilitate other types of attacks. As in other types of IOAM
	  data fields, a malicious attacker can manipulate the field 
	  values in order to create a false illusion of nonexistent network issues 
	  or prevent the detection of actual ones.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.9197'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.cxx-ippm-ioamaggr'?>
	  
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.mzbc-ippm-transit-measurement-option'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.xiao-ippm-ioam-trace-extensions'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.filsfils-ippm-path-tracing'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ravi-ippm-csig'?>
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
